Good evening everyone.
Today's דף daf is, well, we can no longer say we're a
דף daf ahead. So we're going to say today's דף daf is
קלו עמוד ב. Kuf Lamed Vav Amud Bet. We're right in the
middle, we're half דף daf ahead. We're 136b. We start the last
line on קלו עמוד א, Kuf Lamed Vav Amud Aleph, הכותב נכסיו
לבנו לאחר מותו. Hakosav Nechasav Livno Le'achar Moso. So here we get
to the end of the משנה, Mishnah, somebody which is the consequence
of somebody who writes the title of his property to his son,
but he is going to retain the פירות peirot while he's alive.
This is not necessarily to be a type of a will. The
רשבם Rashbam gave an example that he wants to sort of shield
his property from his wife and his second set of kids. Whatever
the case is, he writes over the title but he continues to
get the פירות. peirot. And the משנה Mishnah said that nobody can
sell more than they have. If the father sells to another person,
he has sold the right of eating the פירות peirot while he's
alive, but he hasn't sold the property, he doesn't own the property
anymore. If the son sells it, well, the person who buys from
the son doesn't get the פירות, peirot, the father still has the
פירות, peirot, the person who buys from the son only gets once
the father dies. So let's take a look now at the גמרא.
Gemara. איתמר, Itmar, מכר בן בחיי האב ומת הבן בחיי האב. machar
ben bechayay ha'av umes haben bechayay ha'av. So the son sold while
the father was alive. So as the משנה Mishnah teaches us, if
the father then dies, the son sells to ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven
will get once the father dies. Okay, but let's say the son
dies before the father, and then the father dies. Does ראובן Reuven
still get? So logically, you would think yes, the son sold ראובן
Reuven anything the son had, which was title to the property, no
right to the פירות peirot until the father died. He sells it
to this guy ראובן. Reuven. So even if the son isn't alive
anymore, ראובן Reuven already bought it, and once the father died,
ראובן's Reuven ownership fully actualizes. But the גמרא's Gemara not so sure.
So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, so says רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
לא קנה לוקח, lo kanah lokeach, nope, ראובן Reuven doesn't have anything.
וריש לקיש אמר, veResh Lakish amar, קנה לוקח, kanah lokeach, ראובן Reuven
does get and now he has full property. So what's the issue?
רבי יוחנן אמר לא קנה לוקח קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי. Rabbi
Yochanan amar lo kanah lokeach kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf dami. Because here's
the thing. The father here has, I don't know what happened to
my eraser, I didn't have my eraser.
Anyway,
look at here. So the father gave inheritance to the son. Okay,
yes, okay, so here's the dad, okay, and here's the son, I
mean he doesn't have to be a kid, but just for visual,
okay, so he says, here's the stuff, מכאן
ולאחר מיתה. mikan ule'achar misah. So you keep on that and I'll
keep like here, I'll keep the trees, the פירות peirot as it
were, until after I die. That's what the father says, okay? So
then who has the קניין פירות? kinyan peirot? The father. The son
has the קניין הגוף. kinyan haguf. And then he's going, the question
is, selling it to this other guy.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait. The kid gets the פירות peirot or
the גוף? guf?
The גוף guf for now, the פירות peirot later, מכאן... mikan...
Ah, the father, the father
gets the
פירות peirot and the kid gets title to the land, okay, right.
And then the kid goes ahead and he, but before he dies,
he sells this, okay, and then he dies. All right, so now
the point is like this. When he's sold the גוף, guf, the
father still had the rights to all the benefits from that property.
The father had the קניין פירות. kinyan peirot. So if we say
the קניין פירות kinyan peirot is כקניין הגוף, kekinyan haguf, then the
father is the one who is perceived of effectively of having title.
If you're the one who benefits from it, so even though in
theory the son has title, the father in practice is the one
who has the real benefit, so that's as if he is the
effective owner,
not the technical owner, but the effective owner, that's קניין פירות כקניין
הגוף. kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf. So if the father is seen as
the real owner, then what it's saying is the son really can't
sell the title.
Like a טעות ta'us then?
The title well, yes, but here's the difference. What did the son
sell? So according to the idea that the father is the real
owner, what the son... the son has nothing right now. What the
son is selling is I am selling to you ראובן Reuven the
right that I have in this property. What I have in this
property right now is nothing real, nothing actualized. I have a title
that doesn't mean anything yet. But what I do have is that
that right will actualize when Dad dies, okay? So I'm not selling
you the actual title, I'm not an owner of the property yet.
I am only somebody who has some type of a stake with
some future benefit in the property. Future sale, something like that. Well,
okay, it's not exactly. But okay, anyway, so that would be the
idea. From that perspective, if the son is alive and the father
dies, then the son's rights materialize, and then they transfer on, and
then the sale is valid, okay? But that's only because there really,
he really didn't sell anything yet. So what he's... The sold was
essentially of like, you know, when my, like, like, you'll get it
through me when I, yeah, you'll get it through me when I
get it. Okay. So then if he's alive, he gets it through
him. But if he's dead, then, then, then he doesn't own anything
now, and the son isn't getting anything now, so there's nothing for
him to get. That's the idea of קנין פירות כקנין הגוף, kinyan
peiros k'kinyan haguf, and
since it's קנין הגוף, kinyan haguf, the son really wasn't in a
position to sell any real ownership in the property. All he could
do was sort of sell to this other guy the right to
get it once I get it. Okay?
So then that other guy would buy under those conditions because he's
willing to take the
risk, right, that
the father, that the son will predecease the father.
No, he's going to take the risk that the father will predecease
the son.
Right, right. So that's the idea. The idea is, it's not really
fully explained what that is that he's transferring, but the basic point
is, if קנין פירות כקנין הגוף, kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf, the son
is not seen as an owner at this stage. And since he's
not an owner, he can't even sell what he has. So all
he can sort of do is sort of sell the right to
get it once I get it, once he gets it. And therefore
if he dies first, this guy gets nothing. Let's just finish there.
That's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. ריש לקיש אמר: Reish Lakish
amar, קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan haguf
dami. No, the father is not the owner, the son is the
owner. The son actually sold the actual title itself, and therefore even
if the son dies, once the father's rights of the פירות peiros
go away, this guy already owned the title. The rights of the
father's פירות peiros go away when the father dies, and now he
gets the פירות. peiros. The son actually was the owner and was
able to sell the actual title. Yes.
In the first opinion, doesn't it make sense to the son's interest,
for example, like the reason the father's giving it to the son
so they wouldn't maybe have to give it to his wife or
something? Right. And also, is there a question of whether it should
go to the son's heirs if say he didn't sell it?
If he didn't sell it, right,
and he passes away, shouldn't it go to the son's heirs then?
Right, in other words, it's his to pass on, yes, but not
to sell.
Correct. So that is a good point. When we say קנין פירות
כקנין הגוף, kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf, like that's what I sort of
was trying to sort of walk that tightrope. The son does actually
technically have title. So this guy, for example, in this case, this
guy goes ahead and marries another woman, she doesn't have a lien
on this title, because he doesn't have title anymore, the son does
technically have the title. But one way of thinking about it is
he might have the title but he's not the owner, okay? He
doesn't have a role and a status to play as the owner
yet if קנין פירות כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf dami.
So, since it's no longer legally registered as the father's property, right,
if he marries a new woman she doesn't get liens, okay? And
if he dies, his new children don't get it, because it's no
longer legally registered as his property. It is legally registered as the
son's property. So you're right, if this guy wasn't here and the
son died, right, and the רשב"א Rashba actually makes this point, it
would pass on to his kids, okay? Because it is legally registered
in his name. But because he doesn't have any actual practical benefit
or control right now, he's not in a position of power to
do anything with that title. So he's not in a position of
power to transfer that title to somebody else. Okay, so one way
maybe of conceptualizing it is that, well he can't, right, he can't
sell it to someone, but he could die and pass it on
to his own kids, okay? So one way of saying it is
that if קנין פירות כקנין הגוף, kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf, he's not
conceptually, he's not conceptualized as the בעלים. baalim. He's not conceptualized as
the owner with the powers of the owner in terms of his
sort of personal status and power and roles. But if you want
to know whose, under whose name is this property registered, sure, it's
registered under his name. He just doesn't have any rights and control
over it, okay? No, right, the father cannot sell it, that is
correct. Now we're going to get into a complicated case where, whatever,
we'll see something a little more complicated, but yes, that is correct.
And the רשב"א Rashba makes a, very a very clarifying point, that
if the son dies, yeah, and the לוקח lokeach is still alive,
right, and then the father dies, still the field goes to the
יורשים yorshim of the father.
Right, if the son dies
and then the father dies, the לוקח lokeach doesn't say, well the
father's dead so now it's,
well that's exactly what we just said. Yeah, yeah, yeah, the son
doesn't sell to the, yeah, yeah, yeah. Correct, so the sale does
not go through. Okay, so now, so now let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. All right, so, okay, והא אתפלגו
בחדא זימנא, v'ha itp'lagu b'chada zimna,
one minute, why do they have to say this debate here? That's
a classic רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש Reish Lakish debate, where
they קנין פירות כקנין הגוף kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf or not. דאתמר,
d'itmar, it was taught, המוכר שדה לפירות, hamocher sadeh l'peiros,
somebody sells his field for fruit. So it's a little the reverse.
He retains the title and sells somebody else the fruit. So I
sold Michael, Michael now owns my, I have this wonderful beautiful. A
pomegranate orchard and Michael owns it for the sake of the fruit.
I have the straight out title and he has the גוף לפירות,
guf l'peiros, he owns it for its fruit. Okay? רבי יוחנן אמר
מביא וקורא, Rabbi Yochanan amar meivi v'korei, right? Michael has to bring
those pomegranates to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and do מקרא ביכורים
mikra bikkurim on the first ones of them. Because he can say
על האדמה שנתתה לי, al ha'adama she'nasata li, the land you gave
me. Even though it's registered in my name, since he owns the
land for its fruit, that's an effective, that's the real world benefit
of the land. That's considered אדמה שנתתה לי, adama she'nasata li, it's
my land. All right, good point.
Even though he doesn't have title to the land.
Well right, but his קניין הפירות kinyan hapeiros is like a קניין
הגוף. kinyan haguf. Now again, the reason I'm saying it very precisely,
it's not that Michael bought a future in the fruit and he
owns the fruit, right, he owns the land for its fruit. He
has a right, a right of what's it called, usufruct, right, right,
it is the right in the land for its fruit. It is
not a buying of the future fruits. Okay, and therefore he has
a certain ownership in the land and even though it's not the
title and he can't go ahead and like build a building on
the land, okay, the fact that he has it for its fruit
is enough to identify him as the owner and to say אדמה
שנתתה
לי.
adama she'nasata
li.
Can't chop down a tree.
Correct. That's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. ריש לקיש אמר, Reish
Lakish amar, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, I'm sorry, ריש לקיש אמר,
Reish Lakish amar, sorry, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר, amar: רבי יוחנן
אמר מביא וקורא, Rabbi Yochanan amar meivi v'korei, ריש לקיש אמר מביא
ואינו קורא. Reish Lakish amar meivi v'eino korei. He brings but he
doesn't say אדמה שנתתה לי. adama she'nasata li. רבי יוחנן אמר מביא
וקורא Rabbi Yochanan amar meivi v'korei דקסבר קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי.
d'kasavar kinyan peiros k'kinyan guf dami. He's like he's the owner and
he can say it's my land. ריש לקיש אמר מביא ואינו קורא
Reish Lakish amar meivi v'eino korei דקסבר קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף
דמי. d'kasavar kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan guf dami. It's your fruit but
it's not your land. You can't say אדמה שנתתה לי. adama she'nasata
li. So תוספות Tosafos and the רשב"ם Rashbam say, so if it's
not your land why does he have to bring the fruit altogether?
So the רשב"ם Rashbam wants to say there's some middle level where
it's enough his that he has to bring it but it's not
enough that he can say, make that declaration אדמה שנתתה לי, adama
she'nasata li, whereas תוספות Tosafos says that the bringing is only דרבנן.
drabbanan. Once it's not considered his land, there's no דאורייתא d'oraisa obligation
to bring.
More of a reminder?
Yeah exactly, you know it's appropriate to bring, at the end of
the day you're taking the fruit from the land, like maybe it'll
be confused with other cases. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
if they've already had that debate why do they have to repeat
it here? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר לך
רבי יוחנן, amar lach Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say
if you'd like like this. Here's why I had to repeat my
position here. אף על גב דבעלמא קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי, af
al gav d'be'alma kinyan peiros k'kinyan guf dami, even though normally he
holds קניין פירות כקניין הגוף kinyan peiros k'kinyan guf in this case
and therefore the father retained the practical sense of owner and the
son not and the son couldn't really sell the property, okay, that's
obviously my normal opinion, okay, הכא איצטריך. hacha itzt'rich.
I had to repeat my position by the ביכורים. bikkurim. Why did
I have to repeat my position by the ביכורים? bikkurim? סלקא דעתך
אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I might have thought, wait wait no, am
I saying this? No, הכא hacha in our case. Yeah, in our
case, thank you. I got it reversed. Okay. Even though normally I
hold קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי kinyan peiros k'kinyan guf dami and
the guy who owns קניין פירות kinyan peiros has to be מביא
וקורא meivi v'korei that you're considered effectively the owner, הכא hacha in
this case by the father and the son, איצטריך. itzt'rich. I had
to repeat my position. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I would
have thought אבא לגבי בריה אחולי אחליה, abba legabi b'rei achulie achlie,
that here, even since it's my son that I'm passing the property
onto, I am willing to basically effectively give him more role, right,
more power and recognize him as the owner. So if it's a
stranger I buy Michael bought קניין פירות kinyan peiros from me, so
he's the owner, he has the קניין פירות. kinyan peiros. Why does
he want to see me as the owner? He wants to be
conceptualized as the owner. I mean it requires him to bring ביכורים
bikkurim but fine that's besides the point. Okay? That's the קניין פירות,
kinyan peiros, it's going to be קניין הגוף. kinyan haguf. But here
where I'm just retaining קניין פירות kinyan peiros and I'm passing on
the גוף guf to my son, okay, maybe it's not so important
for me to retain the title of owner. He's my son at
the end of the day and he's going to get the whole
thing when I die. So let him have the title of owner
and the powers of owner. Now the funny thing is what does
it mean to be מוחל? mochel? Like this would seem to be
a like what is it that I could give to my son
besides that? What am I giving to my son that now makes
him recognize as the owner? Right, my קניין, kinyan, I still do
have the קניין. kinyan. Right, I still do have the legal rights
in the land, the ownership in the land to give me the
פירות. peiros. So what do I do? Am I just saying it's
okay with me if he takes on the role of owner? Is
that something I can give or is that a natural outgrowth of
his real legal ownership? We would think it's a natural outgrowth of
his legal ownership. It's not like a title I can confer, right,
so what exactly am I מוחל mochel that allows him to that
could theoretically allow him to take that title? Right, so that's very
unclear. But anyway it's only a הוה אמינא. hava amina. Don't think
that this case the son would get the title because he's my
son and maybe I want to give him more. At the end
of the day since I still have קניין פירות, kinyan peiros, I'm
still
the. Right, let's see the next slide where this confirms exactly what
Gloria said.
So, קמשמע לן, Kamashmilan, that that doesn't matter that it's my son.
I still have the קנין הגוף, Kinyan Haguf, קנין הפירות, Kinyan Haperos,
that's like a קנין הגוף. Kinyan Haguf. That's the רבי יוחנן Rebi
Yochanan approach. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would say, אמר ריש לקיש Amar
Reish Lakish would say,
another reason why I had to tell you why why he had
to tell him his position here,
that קנין הפירות לאו כקנין הגוף. Kinyan Haperos lav kekinyan haguf. אע"ג
דבעלמא קנין הפירות לאו כקנין הגוף, Af al gav de'be'alma kinyan haperos
lav kekinyan haguf, sure, that's my general opinion. Michael here who bought
the קנין הפירות Kinyan Haperos in my pomegranate field does not have
to is not קורא. koreh. He's not considered the owner. The guy
with the פירות peros is not considered the owner. הכא איצטריך, Hacha
itztric, here I had to tell you that again, that he's not
the owner. Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitchak amina, כל לגבי נפשיה
אפילו בלאו בריה נפשיה עדיפא ליה, kol legabei nafshieh afilu belav breih
nafshieh adifa leh, exactly what Gloria said, maybe if you're the seller,
whichever power you are retaining for yourself, you are holding onto the
title of ownership. Even if you're giving it to your son. So
if I am the owner of everything and I give my son
the property, since I'm retaining the פירות, peros, I'm retaining the title
of the owner. Even if it's my son. My son, my son,
whatever it doesn't matter. Whatever I'm retaining since I initially had it
all, any element that I would retain, would I would continue to
hold onto that that identity of owner. So if I gave over
the land and I had the פירות, peros, I'd be the owner.
In the reverse, when I sell Michael the פירות peros the קנין
הפירות Kinyan Haperos in my pomegranate field, I'm also the owner. Okay?
Whichever one I retain, I'm the owner because I started having it
all. So as long as I haven't fully divested myself, I should
always be considered the owner. There's a certain logic to that, right?
Okay? So that's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says. Yes, in the
case by Michael, Michael is not the owner, I'm the owner. But
but maybe that's not based on קנין הפירות לאו כקנין הגוף. Kinyan
Haperos lav kekinyan haguf. Maybe that's based on the principle that whatever
ownership the original owner retains, he's always considered the owner. So therefore
you have to tell me the flip case, whether I give Michael
whether I'm the one who's retaining the קנין הגוף Kinyan Haguf I
mean what if Michael if I'm selling the קנין הפירות, Kinyan Haperos,
then fine, he's not the owner I am. But if I'm selling
the גוף, guf, then I'm not the owner. Then the guy with
the גוף guf is the owner. Okay? So so it's very clarifying
for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that the title of owner goes with
the person who has the גוף guf and it doesn't matter who
started with both titles or who didn't. Yes, Zvi?
It almost feels like giving your kid an allowance, right? I mean
like he's borrowing money but you have to pay you back. It's
like what's the difference? I guess it's all coming from the same
source.
Right. It's like it doesn't matter, he's the one who retains the
the principle of it.
Well, okay, the analogy isn't exactly precise because in that case, you
know, it is the principle itself, but yes.
I was thinking if he gives him the קנין הפירות, Kinyan Haperos,
that he has the first hand he's not the owner, but he
has the first hand to buy the property.
Oh, like a right he has the first right, like a right
of first refusal. That's interesting. We have concepts like that of דינא
דבר מצרא, Dina DeBar Metzra, who has a fighter first refusal.
Yeah, we don't translate it that way, but I hear the logic
behind that. If I have the פירות, peros, I should it's almost
like a דינא דבר מצרא. Dina DeBar Metzra. If you have to
if you're selling a neighboring lot and you have to offer it
to me because I have a bordering lot, then if you're selling
the land from under my trees, you should have to give me
the right of first refusal. That's an interesting question. Maybe we would
apply דינא דבר מצרא Dina DeBar Metzra to that. It's a very
like logically you're right, I mean you know, definitely definitely be that
case that I should have the right of first refusal. I don't
know, that's a good that's a very good question. Okay, but the
bottom line is the combination of these two clarify that for ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, it's a general principle that קנין הפירות לאו כקנין
הגוף דמי, Kinyan Haperos lav kekinyan haguf dami, and it is not
what Gloria very reasonably suggested that maybe it's just the original owner
either way he retains title. No, it's קנין הפירות Kinyan Haperos is
not קנין הגוף, Kinyan Haguf, the קנין הגוף Kinyan Haguf guy is
the guy who's considered to be the owner. Yes.
So is there some kind of legal fiction going on in terms
of this thing with the son, when he passes it to his
son and then he avoids the wife's being involved? Right. It's kind
of a legal fiction that
Well, I don't know why it's a legal fiction. I mean it's
it's certainly a legal device.
It's good for that but it's not good for this.
Right. I mean so it's true, it's I hear the point, meaning
it's not full ownership. Yes, right. You're saying like not only is
it
not full ownership that the son isn't benefiting from it yet, but
it's not even full ownership and that the son isn't even in
any way recognized yet as the owner.
No, but in a legal fiction sense but still it allows the
father to avoid...
Right. So the son is in no way recognized as the owner
and but still he's enough of the owner that it's shielding the
property. Right. Yeah, that's true, that's definitely true. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, איבעיא להו רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש.
Ibaia lehu Rebi Yochanan ve'Reish Lakish. So now we're going to get
into this debate. Okay, but about קנין הפירות קנין הגוף, Kinyan Haperos
Kinyan Haguf, but specifically about... specifically, not a generic debate, because you
know, maybe there's different ways you could decide it between a ביכורים
Bikkurim case and this and a case like about selling the property,
you know, and then dying, which is, right, the case here. So
we're going to try to focus more on the consequences of the
idea of קנין פירות כקנין הגוף Kinyan Peirot ke-Kinyan Haguf in this
case. That the guy with the גוף guf sold it and then
dropped dead. Was that sale still retained or not? Did he really
have the property enough to sell it? So let's take a look.
איזה ר' יוחנן וריש לקיש? Aizeh Rabbi Yochanan ve-Reish Lakish? Rabbi Yochanan
is the one who says קנין פירות כקנין הגוף, Kinyan Peirot ke-Kinyan
Haguf, asked on ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. נכסיי לך ואחריך יירש פלוני
ואחריו יירש פלוני. Nechasai lecha ve-acharecha yirash ploni ve-acharayv yirash ploni.
Okay,
so this guy says, okay, we've seen cases like this, okay. Here's
the guy, he says נכסיי לך. nechasai lecha. Whoops, I don't know
why I did that, נכסיי לך. nechasai lecha. מתנה? Matana? Yeah,
well, it's a מתנה, matana, but it might also be like a
type of effectively like the שכיב מרע, shachiv mera, well it doesn't
have to be שכיב מרע, shachiv mera, but anyway. מתנה לך ואחריך
לפלוני ואחריו יירש פלוני. Matana lecha ve-acharecha le-ploni ve-acharayv yirash ploni. Now
because there are all these אחריו, acharayv, we're assuming how is it
that I, once I give you property, once I give Reuven property,
how is it who I can control who Reuven's property goes to
after Reuven dies? Once it's Reuven's property, it's Reuven's property. How am
I going to control that, how can I sort of stipulate that
I'm giving it to you and after and after you it's going
to go on right from Reuven, from Reuven to Shimon to Levi?
I mean once I've given it to Shimon, once I've given, so
ah, so one thing you could do, I wouldn't say maybe it's
a תנאי tenai but maybe also another way to do it would
be like a קנין לזמן, kinyan le-zman, right? Why can't I sort
of be like מקנה makne it to Reuven for like, you know,
what was it, Hong Kong, right, was
99 years.
You know what, they eventually found out that 99 years eventually comes
about, comes around some,
so it sounds like forever away when you're doing it, right? But
anyway, so why don't you say I'm being מקנה makne it to
you for, you know, for 50 years or I'm מקנה makne it
to you well those set a תנאי tenai but תנאי tenai is
a little different because תנאי tenai would mean that it would retroactively.
Okay, maybe one way or the other. Anyway, for the duration of
your life, and then afterwards, then, and then you only own it
for whatever your life span is going to be, 80 years, we'll
figure it out once you die, 80 years, and then afterwards and
you know, I'm being מקנה makne it to Shimon, and then I'm
being מקנה makne to Shimon whatever. So that's possible, but it's not
exactly clear how the mechanism would work, because if this guy is
dead when Reuven dies, how can he מקנה makne something,
can guy say I מקנה makne this piece of property to Michael
for 100 years from now? If I'm not around 100 years from
now and I no longer owning it, how could I be מקנה
makne it to him, right, 100 for, so like what exactly would
be that mechanism? So Michael wants to say it's a תנאי tenai
and so what's the תנאי? tenai? You have to give it to
him, and if you're not מקנה makne it to him then retroactively,
but Reuven dies. So what exactly is the act of the תנאי?
tenai? So it's not exactly clear the mechanism. The easiest mechanism to
understand is that what this guy is doing is he's מקנה makne
the entire גוף guf to Levi right now, because Levi is the
one who it's going to end up with, and he's giving the
פירות peirot to Reuven for as long as Reuven lives and the
פירות peirot to Shimon for as long as Shimon lives. And after
Reuven and Shimon die, then Levi is going to get the actual
קרקע. karka. That's how we would normally conceptualize what that is. Okay,
so these two have a קנין פירות kinyan peirot and this guy
has a קנין הגוף. kinyan haguf.
Would this be very inelegant but could you have a separate שטר
shtar for each guy, make a קנין kinyan to each one of
those people and the שטר shtar would be post-dated?
Yeah, that's what I said. You could sort of say I'm being
מקנה makne it to you for 50 years, 50 years from, but
the question is can I be מקנה makne something to somebody that
will only take effect after I'm already dead? Right, so it's not
clear.
Even if you've got the שטר shtar that wouldn't.
Yeah, but after I'm dead, it's no longer my property, so can
I be מקנה makne to you somebody, can I be מקנה makne
you my, my land 200 years from now? It'll take effect in
200 years, you know, after I'm no longer around, I don't own
it 200 years from now. Anyway, so it's not clear. The easiest
thing to say is I מקנה makne the קרקע karka to Levi
and I'm giving them the rights of the פירות peirot in that
order.
So then before Levi's for tens of years, so then once Levi
dies, it'll go to his kids. Oh, you mean and if he's,
right, if he's dead by the time it gets to him it'll
probably, right according to this it would go to his kids, he
doesn't have to be alive to receive it because he already received
it. Right, right, and Shimon might not have to be alive to
receive the פירות peirot because he already received the פירות, peirot, right?
But let's take a look at what happens. Okay, so, or rather
the right, so the גמרא Gemara says נכסיי לך ואחריך יירש פלוני
ואחריו יירש פלוני, Nechasai lecha ve-acharecha yirash ploni ve-acharayv yirash ploni, מת
ראשון קנה שני מת שני קנה שלישי, Met rishon kana sheni met
sheni kana shlishi,
so if everybody dies in the right order it works, if everybody
does us the convenience of dying in the right order. Now, מת
שני בחיי ראשון. Met sheni be-chayei rishon.
Now Shimon here died, okay, before Reuven died. Okay, so now what's
going to
So in that case, since the the gift cannot continue down the
chain, the assumption here is, is that לוי Levi can only get
it if he gets it through שמעון. Shimon. Okay? So since the
gift cannot continue down the chain because he can't get it through
שמעון Shimon because שמעון Shimon never received it from ראובן, Reuven, the
פירות peros at least. So then it's not going to go all
the way down. So what happens to it? So it says it
stays in ראובן's Reuven control. Since ראובן Reuven cannot, since the chain
can't continue, it was ראובן's, Reuven so now ראובן Reuven died it
will pass on to ראובן's Reuven heirs. Now the question the גמרא's
Gemara going to say is that only makes sense if you say,
this whole thing is very complicated, but anyway, but you can understand
the broad strokes. It only makes sense if you consider ראובן's Reuven
קנין הפירות כקנין הגוף. kinyan haperos k'kinyan haguf. If you say he
was a virtual owner and since he was a virtual owner of
the גוף guf itself, he didn't really have title yet, but he
had a virtual title because he had קנין פירות, kinyan peros, and
there's nobody to receive the title, nobody the right person who's supposed
to receive isn't going to receive, so then the title would revert
to him. Okay, and that's why you would say it would become
effectively his title because the person to receive it is not, he
was the he was the virtual owner so then ultimately he would
become the real owner of the title and it would go down
to his heirs.
If you say קנין הפירות לאו כקנין הגוף, kinyan haperos lav k'kinyan
haguf, then לוי Levi should get it.
If you say it's לאו כקנין הגוף, lav k'kinyan haguf, no, לוי
Levi should get it because לוי Levi is effectively the real גוף.
guf. Yeah, but לוי Levi doesn't isn't going to get it because
the conditions aren't being met, so the original giver should get it.
Okay, so I'm
not you're not the owner, you're not the owner because your קנין
הפירות kinyan haperos doesn't make you קנין הגוף, kinyan haguf, you're never
going to get the קנין הגוף kinyan haguf because the conditions aren't
going to be met, so the only person for it to go
to is the actual original owner.
How can the original guy, how can the original guy make the
קנין kinyan for the פירות peros also after his death, right? In
other words, he's he's died. So if he tells me like yeah,
you can't make a you can't make that type of קנין kinyan
on the גוף guf like you know, over the last 200 years
you won't be alive.
Yeah, because I think it's different. It's different because I like have
a perpetual I think it's different. I think that I own the
I can sell rights to something.
I hear it's different but I can't say to myself why.
I don't know, like if I have,
right, get my bearings right.
Yeah, I think it's different. If I own this plot of land,
I can sell you the the the פירות peros from this land,
the rights to this land from from 100 years from now, from
the year 2100 to the year 2150, right, because I because right
now when I am selling you those rights, I fully own the
land, so I can sell you like a piece of that. I
can sell you, right? I don't know, I you're right, I have
to articulate it better, but to me I think it makes sense
that I can't sell the land once it's no longer in my
control and once I'm dead, but whatever. However it is, this is
how we're conceptualizing. You're right, it does have to be articulated better.
But anyway, okay, so that's the point. So anyway, if he's כקנין
הגוף, k'kinyan haguf, I understand why effectively he's considered the owner, לוי
Levi doesn't have the קנין הגוף kinyan haguf anymore, so it passes
down. So that's his point. He says like this, he says, וחזר
ולחבר ואחריך י- v'chazar v'lechaver v'achareicha yi- wait a minute. So it
says מת ראשון יחזרו נכסים ליורשי ראשון. Meis Rishon yachzeru nechasim leyorshei
Rishon. They go to the to the to the heirs of the
first. ואי איתא ליורשי נותן מיבעי ליה, V'ee sisa leyorshei nosein mibaei
lei, but according to you that the first guy ראובן Reuven wasn't
never considered an owner, so and the original guy who's supposed to
and the guy who's supposed to receive the קנין הגוף kinyan haguf
can't receive it, then it should revert to the original owner. אמר
ליה כבר תרגמה רב הושעיא בבבל אחריך שאני. Amar lei kevar turgemei
Rav Oshaya beVavel achareicha shani. No, רב הושעיא Rav Oshaya already explained
this, this is different because of אחריך. achareicha. The using the word
אחריך achareicha is different. וכן רמי בר חמא קמיה דרבא, v'chein Rami
bar Chama kamyei d'Rava, וכן רמי בר חמא קמיה דרבא, v'chein Rami
bar Chama kamyei d'Rava, ואמר v'amar he got up in front of
רבא, Rava, ואמר אחריך שאני, v'amar achareicha shani, אחריך achareicha is different.
Now what does it mean? Now what does the word אחריך achareicha
do that is different? Okay, so what the word what it does
is, and the רשב"ם Rashbam also adds you didn't just say אחריך,
achareicha, you said
אחריך יירש פלוני. Achareicha yirash ploni. So יירש yirash means, no, no,
no, we misconceptualized this. This is not that לוי Levi has the
גוף guf and you guys get the פירות. peros. The word אחריך
achareicha means that whatever you got, you are getting it full, and
afterwards it's fully passing over to the next guy, and after him
fully to the next guy. It's not
like גוף ללוי ופירות לך ואחריך פירות לשמעון. Guf leLevi u'peros lecha
v'achareicha peros leShimen. That would be what we described. No, he said,
you're going to get it all, and after you it's all going
to go to שמעון, Shimen, and after שמעון Shimen it's all going
to go to לוי. Levi. So this means, and although we were
sort of saying. And it's hard to exactly understand how the mechanism
works, but we got it wrong, guys. Actually, somehow you were able
to do this. You get the גוף guf and the קרקע karka
for your life, and then שמעון Shimon gets the גוף guf and
the קרקע, karka, and then לוי Levi gets it. Somehow, by using
those words and however the mechanism is, I am able to actually
transfer ownership to you, full ownership, and say after you die, it
fully transfers to שמעון, Shimon, and after שמעון, Shimon, it fully transfers
to לוי. Levi. I am able to do that, even if I've
been dead for 100 years by the time that לוי Levi or
לוי'ס Levi's kids get it. So since that's what we're actually doing,
because you said the word אחריך acharecha and with also the רשב"ם
Rashbam says יירש, yerash, so now it makes sense. שמעון... Shimon... if
שמעון Shimon dies, of course שמעון'ס Shimon's kids are going to get
it. שמעון Shimon had it 100 percent. So if you can't continue
the chain, שמעון'ס Shimon's kids will get it. Yes, Jenna.
If it's really full ownership, if שמעון Shimon doesn't like decide to
just like sell it to somebody else?
Right. So we're going actually get to the question of can שמעון
Shimon break, consciously break the chain? Maybe שמעון Shimon can intentionally sell
it to somebody else, right? Now you've got a whole קנוניא knunya
going. Because what שמעון Shimon would do is שמעון Shimon would say,
look buddy, I'll sell it to you, it'll break the chain, you'll
own it, right, and you know, and then you know I get
a kickback, well I don't even get a kickback, you're actually giving
me money. Smart thing to do would be for שמעון Shimon to
have a sale that would be take effect the minute before he
dies, right? Break the chain and everybody else is out. So we're
actually going to get to that. That actually is, yes, going to
be a consequence of saying this. Yes.
Is this, I don't know if this is a different kind of
question, is this type of case
הלכתית halachically gendered in any way? In other words, those people could
be women, right?
Absolutely. Absolutely.
Absolutely.
שרה, Sarah, רבקה, Rivka, מרים, Miriam, etc., right?
Absolutely. We'll do it next time that way. Okay.
Although I take umbrage at the fact that all your men are
always bold, there's never
any רחל, Rachel, שרה, Sarah, yeah, see it works with the same
first letters. But now we'll have to do like that. That's also
sexist. Okay, anyway, fine. Moving on. All right, so it says like
this. Okay, שאני. shani. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. והתניא, ve-hatanya, one minute,
we have a ברייתא braita that says
יחזרו ליורשי נותן. yachzeru l'yorshei noten. Wait! That's all very nice. Now
we've explained why there's it's when this gets broken, it goes down
to רחל'ס Rachel's kids here, because we said either because קנין פירות
כקנין הגוף, kinyan peirot k'kinyan haguf, קנין פירות כקנין הגוף, kinyan peirot
k'kinyan haguf,
okay, which is basically, which is
which
is what do you call it, which is רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan,
okay, or we said אחריך, acharecha, right? Because of אחריך, acharecha, she
actually had the גוף, guf, equals גוף. guf. Okay, that was ריש
לקיש. Reish Lakish. Either way we've explained why it's why if the
chain gets broken, it stops at רחל Rachel and goes to רחל'ס
Rachel's kids. But we have a ברייתא braita that actually says that
it reverts back if if שרה Sarah here dies, it reverts back
to the original giver. Okay? So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan could explain
that, right? Oh, well actually, no, well let's take a look.
So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan would explain why would it revert back
to the original giver? So that would be if you would sort
of take the position of קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף. kinyan peirot
lav k'kinyan haguf.
And then אחריך acharecha is not different.
Well certainly, right. Well רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan never said אחריך שאני.
acharecha shani. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan was saying it was קנין פירות
כקנין הגוף, kinyan peirot k'kinyan haguf, there's my little trees or whatever.
And if you say that actually it goes back all the way
here, that would be the position קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף. kinyan
peirot lav k'kinyan haguf. Okay, but according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
I'm going to read this גמרא Gemara like תוספות Tosafot right now.
According to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, if אחריך שאני, acharecha shani, we're
assuming that everybody holds אחריך שאני. acharecha shani. That what you're making
a claim is that אחריך acharecha means the entire גוף guf and
פירות. peirot. So if that's true, why could it would anybody ever
say that it could revert back up to the original giver? So
the obvious answer is going to be, fine, not everybody holds that
אחריך שאני. acharecha shani. Okay, so let's take a look. Right, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: והתניא יחזרו ליורשי נותן, ve-hatanya yachzeru
l'yorshei noten,
so the גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא. tannai hi. This issue of
if אחריך שאני acharecha shani or not is is a debate of
תנאי. tannai. So if it's שאני, shani, then yes, it makes you
into the owner, and if אחריך acharecha just means your normal קנין
פירות, kinyan peirot, then according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, normal קנין
פירות, kinyan peirot, you're not the owner and the original guy is
the owner. דתניא דתניא בברייתא, d'tanya d'tanya b'vraita, נכסי לך ואחריך לפלוני.
nechasai lach v'acharecha l'ploni.
Okay,
so this is the case. היורש הראשון hayoresh harishon מכר ואכל. machar
v'achal. There you go, Jenna, your case. So comes along, right, רחל,
Rachel, and she goes ahead and she says, I'm not going to
let שרה Sarah get it after I die. I go ahead... she
went ahead and she sold it. She intentionally broke the chain. Okay,
was she able to do it? Is she considered an owner, right?
Was she able to do it? So it says like this, it
says: השני מוציא מיד הלקוחות דברי רבי. hasheni motzi miyad halakochot divrei
Rabbi.
Rabbi says, you know, שרה Sarah can come back and say... Ha
ha, good try there Rachel. Okay, you only, you were not an
owner to sell it. So you maybe sold your right of fruit
and benefit or whatever it is you had, but you weren't an
owner and I'm going to go ahead and take the title back.
Okay, so that means that Rachel is not an owner.
Why did מכר ואכל? machar v'achal?
Yeah, the רשב"ם Rashbam just says it's just a way of saying
like that a way of like saying you benefited from it yourself.
You put it in your own bank account and you're not passing
it down to Sarah there. Okay. But רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer אין לשני אלא מה ששייר ראשון. ein
lashinei ela ma sheshiyer rishon. No, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says, no, Sarah only gets what Rachel decides to leave
over to her. If Rachel wants to sell it, then she sold
it. Okay, so there's the direct debate, it's a case of אחריך,
acharecha, was Rachel in a position to sell it. So one way
to say the debate is, is קניין הפירות כקניין הגוף. kinyan hapeiros
ke-kinyan haguf. That's presumably how רב יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan would say it.
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, who always says קניין פירות kinyan peiros is
not כקניין הגוף, ke-kinyan haguf, would say for רשב"ג Rashbag that Rachel
could sell it, it's because אחריך acharecha is שאני. shani. So for
רבי, Rebbi, that Rachel could not sell it, it would have to
be because אחריך acharecha is not שאני. shani. אחריך acharecha doesn't give
you title. That that issue of does the word אחריך acharecha actually
give you title, that is debated. Okay. So, שאני shani is different.
שונה shoneh is different. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now by the way, nobody's asking, I was waiting for somebody to
ask, so if you don't ask, I'll ask on your behalf, which
is, if Rachel here because of a קניין הפירות, kinyan hapeiros, let's
take a רב יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan approach, if because of a קניין
הפירות, kinyan hapeiros, Rachel is כקניין הגוף ke-kinyan haguf and sell it
away from Sarah and prevent Sarah from getting it, so why in
the case where we started with where the father basically gives to
his son and gives him the קניין הגוף kinyan haguf and the
father keeps the קניין הפירות, kinyan hapeiros, right, or actually, or another
case, actually, no, that, let's do the case where I sold Michael
my pomegranate orchard, okay, here was and it was a case of
ביכורים, bikkurim, and I sold him my pomegranate orchard, right, and he's
so, and he's מביא וקורא. mevi ve-korei. He has the קניין הפירות.
kinyan hapeiros. Does anybody think that Michael can now go ahead and
sell that land out from under me? His,
even though he's got the קניין הפירות, kinyan hapeiros, it's my land.
He can't go ahead. His being like an owner might allow him
to bring ביכורים, bikkurim, it might have other consequences, but does it
allow him to now sell the land out from under me? The
answer is obviously no. But the difference here is the following. I
am retaining my original land. I'm holding onto it. Even if he's
a quasi-owner because of קניין הפירות, kinyan hapeiros, he can't take out
my land from away from me. In this case, the person divested
himself fully from his property. And assuming אחריך acharecha isn't שאני, shani,
okay, we'll get rid of this one down here, assuming אחריך acharecha
isn't שאני, shani, he gave the פירות peiros to one person and
the land to another. And this land ownership has not yet like
actualized. This person is only going to get the land at like,
it's, you know what I mean, this person's like way down, it's
yet like a not yet actualized thing and the original owner divested
himself. So here,
so right, so if קניין הפירות kinyan hapeiros is כקניין הגוף ke-kinyan
haguf that actually allows Rachel to step into this almost like no
man's land and claim and say, oh, I'm the only owner around
here. Who was that that says when was that, was that Al
Haig, I don't know whatever, when
remember when Reagan was, I'm going back a few years, was it
that thing where he was like, there's a period where he wasn't
well or somebody and James Baker said like, I'm the boss, nobody
remember this? Am I dating myself? Anyway, whatever. Okay, in the West
Wing, yes, right. There's always these questions about right about like exactly
the line of whatever, I'm the boss, nobody is claiming the ownership
here, I'm going to step in. Okay, so the original person isn't
the owner, this yes they have an entitlement but it's not yet
actualized. So as opposed to this case, here if קניין הפירות kinyan
hapeiros is כקניין הגוף, ke-kinyan haguf, you really can step in and
be the owner and therefore Rachel could sell it away. So ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, so that is the position of רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says, Rachel could sell it away, either because קניין הפירות כקניין
הגוף kinyan hapeiros ke-kinyan haguf or because אחריך שאני acharecha shani and
she really does have the גוף, guf, okay, yes.
Is the רשב"ם Rashbam meaning that the תנאי tnai he is not
a מחלוקת machlokes about שאני? shani?
Yes, but I didn't want to deal with the רשב"ם. Rashbam. I'm
doing with תוספות. Tosafos.
Okay fine, I understand.
Yes.
Okay, so different from what, it's
different from not saying it. When you don't say it, you only
get קניין הפירות. kinyan hapeiros. When you do say it, you get
קניין הגוף, kinyan haguf,
okay, alright, let's move on. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, I gotta find
this, okay, a
bit convoluted reading the רשב"ם Rashbam then.
Where? Yeah, I mean, yes. Okay, alright, so, alright, so now it
says like this,
right, I'm sorry, it wasn't Baker, Al Haig, at the Reagan assassination
attempt, I'm in charge here. Okay, there was a whole big thing.
Go ahead, go ahead.
Some of you, some of you weren't alive at that time, maybe
one of you, okay, anyway. Moving along, moving along.
I can see the picture in my mind, he got
shot, remember?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, anyway, so the רמב"ם *Rambam* says like
this. Okay. Alright. So. Alright, so now the Gemara says like this.
ורמינהי *U'reminhi*, I'll ask you on this: נכסי לך ואחריך לפלוני *Nechasai
lach ve’achareich liploni*, יורד ראשון ומוכר ואוכל דברי רבי *yored rishon u’mocher
ve’ochel divrei Rabbi*. He’s always got a Baraita that sounds almost exact
opposite. You have this case of אחריך achreich *achareich*. Rabbi says let
Rachel go ahead and sell. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר *Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer*, אין לראשון אלא אכילת פירות peiros בלבד *ein larishon
ela achilat perot bilvad*. No, Rachel only gets the right to the
fruit. What are you talking about? Rabbi says you can sell and
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* says you only get
the right to the fruit? We were just saying the opposite. That
Rabbi said Rachel can’t transfer the property away and רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* said that Rachel could transfer the property
away. They’re totally reversing themselves. It really does sound like that. So
the Gemara says: קשיא דרבי אדרבי ודרבן שמעון בן גמליאל אדרבן שמעון
בן גמליאל *kashya deRabbi aDeRabbi u’deRabban Shimon ben Gamliel aDeRabban Shimon ben
Gamliel*. So their both statements are in direct opposition. So the easiest
thing to be would be to say they got the names reversed,
but okay, so the Gemara doesn’t. דרבי אדרבי לא קשיא *deRabbi aDeRabbi
lo kashya*. No, it’s not a problem. הא בגופא הא בפירות *ha
begufa ha beperot*. When Rabbi said let Rachel go ahead and sell,
it meant let her sell the fruit. She’s totally able to sell
the fruit that she owns. When Rabbi said that Rachel can’t sell
it away from Sarah was when she was actually trying to sell
the property itself, the underlying property. Okay, so that’s how we reconcile
Rabbi. Now how about רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*?
He said she could sell the underlying property. So what does he
mean when he says she can’t sell? So the Gemara says: דרבן
שמעון אדרבן שמעון בן גמליאל לא קשיא *deRabban Shimon aDeRabban Shimon ben
Gamliel lo kashya*. That’s not difficult. הא לכתחילה הא דיעבד *ha l’chatchila
ha di’eved*. It means if Rachel sold the underlying property, then okay,
she sold it away from Sarah, but she was contravening the will
of the giver. So why does it work? Because it doesn’t matter.
At the end of the day, it might not have been what
you wanted, but you gave me those rights and it’s now mine
and I’m just going to do it. You didn’t make an explicit
stipulation, if you ever try to contravert my conditions here, the whole
gift is not binding.
So she sold
the גוף *guf*.
She sold the גוף *guf*.
Because it is כגוף *keguf*, he’s therefore able, and because the original
owner doesn’t own the גוף *guf*, she’s able to actually sell the
גוף *guf* right now.
She’s not allowed to but it works. You wanted this person to
get it, but this person’s ownership has not actualized, and now effectively
by breaking the chain, she will prevent it from ever actualizing. It
contravenes what you wanted, but you gave her that power, you didn’t
explicitly stipulate that she couldn’t do that, okay, so it works.
The only thing you could say is that that person is either
unethical or
unreliable, which is exactly what the Gemara is going to get to.
So let’s take a look. Okay. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel* said the person Rachel sells it to only gets
the פירות peiros *perot*. It’s a funny way of saying it but
what it means is Rachel should only be selling the פירות *perot*.
But if Rachel actually went ahead and tried and sold the גוף
*guf*, and since Sarah didn’t get the גוף *guf*, it didn’t actualize
yet, and he divested himself, she could sell it away and break
the chain. So the Gemara says like this: אמר אביי Amar Abaye
*amar Abaye*. So now the question of ethics comes up. Okay. איזהו
רשע rasha. ערום *eizehu rasha arum*? Who is a scheming wicked person?
Yeah, I know I would say duplicitous but like a scheming, scheming
wicked person. זה המשיא עצה למכור בנכסים כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל *ze
hamashi eitza limkor benechasim keRabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. That’s somebody, Jenna here,
who comes to her friend Rachel and says, Rachel, I was just
learning the דף יומי daf yomi. *Daf Yomi*, I got some great
advice for you! Why not sell your property away and go ahead
have it take effect a second before you die, your kids will
get the money, and you’ll prevent Sarah from getting the underlying property?
So the interesting thing is that we are saying that Jenna is
the, I wouldn’t say Jenna God forbid, anyway, Jenna’s evil twin sister
is the רשע rasha. *rasha*. But you know who’s not the רשע
rasha. *rasha*? Who’s not the רשע rasha *rasha* here? Rachel. Rachel isn’t
the רשע rasha *rasha*. It’s very interesting. At the end of the
day, Rachel has the power, it is legal. Is it unethical? Okay,
maybe it’s not the most ישרות *yashrus* thing to do, but you
know what?
It’s sort of like חייך וחייך *chayecha vechayecha*, like she’s got her
kids to worry about. I mean she’s at the end of the
day, she’s doing it, it is sort of taking care of her
own needs. Now so she’s not the רשע *rasha*. She’s doing it
because you’re entitled to sort of make a buck in this life.
Okay, it’s not necessarily the best thing to do. We wouldn’t give
you a gold star but we’re not going to call you a
רשע *rasha*. But who needs a somebody who doesn’t stand to gain
from it and therefore all they’re doing is they’re hurting Sarah with
no gain to themselves? So it’s very interesting like we might normally
think אדרבא *adarabba*, like if the person who’s totally acting out of
self... interest at the you know at the sort of disregard of
the benefit of other people, that person is totally selfish and a
רשע and whatever, right? But actually no, like you know, you totally
you have legal power to do it. It's not the nicest thing
to do, nobody again is saying that you're as the most ethical
person but nobody's calling you a רשע. You know you need to
take care of your kids and your family and what not and
you have the right and the power to do it. So it's
interesting, דוקא davka because you're acting out of self-interest that makes you
less of a רשע. So the person who's hurting Sarah
is the broker
is the yeah or the the lawyer. I mean I guess if
the lawyer's being paid they might not be a רשע. No I'm
serious, it's the fact that the person is doing it for with
no benefit to themselves.
Why if I tell you you know what you gotta take care
of you have to think of your
grandchildren, I've become a רשע because I've given you that?
Right so that's also the question. What do you mean no benefit
to yourself? You're giving me this advice because there's times in the
past that I've helped you and because we're friends and because of
whatever. It is very interesting that you know that it's the sort
of the external interlocutor that is more of the רשע than the
actual party himself. And the גמרא Gemara has this elsewhere as well,
this idea about the משיא עצה, masei eitza, you know it's sort
of it's עובר על ריב לא לו over al riv lo lo
is also a phrase in the גמרא. Gemara. עובר על ריב לא
לו, over al riv lo lo, right? You're getting involved in something
that isn't your fight and you know we understand that people act
to serve their best interests, okay? But you getting involved in something
that isn't your fight and helping one party and hurting another party,
it's like no thanks, yes.
It almost feels like it's sort of subverting תורה Torah to to
come and say hey you know you didn't know that you had
this right but because I know all this תורה Torah I can
tell you you have something you didn't know you had.
Yeah you mean it's using your knowledge of תורה Torah to sort
of to that's always the way it is. The more you know
a certain legal system the more you can sort of find those
loopholes and maybe sometimes subvert the larger purpose. But you know but
again we wouldn't blame Rachel if she knew that, we're only blaming
the outsider who's advising her, yeah.
I imagine it as like someone comes to their friend and says
I have this horrible problem like can you help me figure it
out and like oh yeah I went to דף daf יומי.
Right? But like rather like you know I walk out of this
classroom and just start telling everyone did you know that if you
ever get in a situation like this you can do this and
just like spreading it everywhere so that like more and more people
know about it and like
right so like how much are you like the initiator and sowing
this you know discord and how much are you just right
or it's like prove that you can cheat the system, right,
right, so it could be. Exactly, I think it is really fascinating
and this is not the only time that the גמרא Gemara has
this idea that this external interlocutor you know who's just advising somebody
legally about their rights but is subverting the purpose is sort of
seen as like a real troublemaker.
Yeah is there any connection though between the two cases where we
said the previous one was the father giving the land to the
son's title and the question about the פירות and the ownership and
here?
Yes that's what I was saying because she's divested herself of the
property it allows Rachel to step in and say I'm the boss
here, okay? Whereas if she retained the property you didn't fully divest
yourself this kid guy can't come ahead and go ahead and really
sell the property away.
But previous case the
father has the פירות
and the kid had the land.
But yeah but no but again if it's not like a full
divestment then you don't have the ability to do what Rachel can
do over here.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אמר רב יוחנן הלכה כרבי שמעון בן גמליאל. amar Rav Yochanan
halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. Well we might not like it and
it might be a way of subverting certain people's intent but at
the end of the day that's the way we rule like him.
Now the רשב"ם Rashbam points out we actually rule
קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan haguf dami.
So by saying הלכה כרבי שמעון בן גמליאל halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel we're actually saying אחריך לשני. achreich l'sheni. Okay the normal קנין
פירות kinyan peiros
Rachel could not sell the underlying
property, it's לאו כקנין הגוף, lav k'kinyan haguf, מיהא דאינו קורע. miha
d'eino koreia. But if you say אחריך Acharecha. you're actually actually giving
her the property itself, okay? So ומודה
שאם נתנה במתנת שכיב מרע לא עשה כלום. u'modeh she'im netana b'matnat
shachiv mera lo asa klum. Now if Rachel here rather than going
ahead and selling it to somebody else on her deathbed said I
am, this now we get to a very different point which is
very important for מתנת שכיב מרע, matnat shachiv mera, so pay attention,
okay? We're moving away from the קנין פירות כקנין הגוף, kinyan peiros
k'kinyan haguf, I mean we're still in it but on her deathbed
here Rachel basically said I am going to go ahead and give
this as a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shachiv mera to my friend
Devorah, okay?
That's what she said. Now here's the question:
which kicks in first? Her מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shachiv mera takes
effect when she dies. So now she's died, she died at 12:00
midnight at 12:00 midnight and .0001 seconds okay. Right, the
property transfers to דבורה Dvora the second after she died. Or do
we say wait, אחריך יירש פלוני, Acharecha Yerash Ploni, a second after
she died the property transfers to שרה? Sarah? Who does it transfer
to? Because it took effect after she died and both of these
are taking effect after she died. Okay, so let's take a look.
ומודה שאם נתנה במתנת שכיב מרע לא עשתה כלום. U'modeh she'im netanah
b'matnas sh'chiv mera lo asata klum. It doesn't work. Why? מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? אמר אביי Abaye מתנת שכיב מרע לא קנה אלא לאחר
מיתה matnas sh'chiv mera lo kana ela l'achar mita וקדם אחריך. v'kodam
acharecha. This takes place only after she died, and it already went
to שרה. Sarah. But one minute, didn't שרה Sarah also take place
after she died? It said אחריך. acharecha Okay, so there's the גמרא
Gemara is going to distinguish between these two moments in time. You
ready? One is עם גמר מיתה im gmar mita and the other
is לאחר מיתה. l'achar mita.
Did it take place at the moment of death or after the
death? At the moment? At the moment of death? At 12:00 exactly,
that's was when it transferred on to שרה. Sarah. But the gift
of a שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera is only after the moment of
death, at 12:00 and point oh one second. Okay, so now why
should we say that? Okay, why should we say one is at
the moment and one is after? Okay, so cause מתנת שכיב מרע
matnas sh'chiv mera is usually like one way of thinking of מתנת
שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera is like מהיום ולאחר מיתה. me'hayom u'l'achar
mita. The phrase we used before to describe a מתנת בריא matnas
bari that's like a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera is לאחר
מיתה, l'achar mita, after death. And that's normally how we think about
it. Somebody died and then after he died, his property transferred on.
So the real question is why you read אחריך acharecha being at
the moment of death. Okay? But but there's a little difference if
you just think of the words, right, between אחריך Acharecha and לאחר
מיתה. l'achar mita. לאחר מיתה L'achar mita is after you're already dead.
אחריך acharecha is after you, right? So at that moment of death,
you're you no longer have it and need it and somebody else
should so there's like, you know, it's like
if you conceptualize it, here's you as alive, I won't say you,
okay. There you're alive, this is the moment of death, and then
this is the moment of after death. Okay.
So after you means after when you're no longer alive, that
could be at the moment of death. If you just conceptualize it,
you're alive, you're there's the moment of death, and then it's after
you're dead. So after you, well, after you're alive is when at
that moment of death because we no longer call you alive, we
call you you're at the moment of death. Right?
לאחר מיתה L'achar mita is when the ירושה yerusha transfers.
Yes. So think of it as like the two people inherit is
like right the first and the second right next to each other
and like there's nothing in between them. It's like if that person's
not there then it's the second person, right? Whereas like לאחר מיתה,
l'achar mita, there's like some kind of death space that's in between.
Exactly.
Right. Right, so like yeah, so this is exactly. Right, so like
yeah, so this is exactly. I mean, it's that I think that's
just yeah, another way of saying sort of this point, but it's
interesting conceptually. There's the moment of look, this is a whole issue
right now, you know, the whole issue about brain death and people
say like, you know, death is not a moment, right? Death is
like a process. Right? To exactly say this precise. Now this isn't
exactly the point, but there's a similar thing to thinking that we
can say it's sort of like the בין השמשות bein ha'shmashos of
living and dead. To say that we could say a person goes
from living to dead and there is like no transition moment in
between. So the death is the transition moment in between. When the
person stops being alive but it's not he's already dead. Okay? And
therefore אחריך means after the alive state, whereas לאחר מיתה l'achar mita
or מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera or ירושה yerusha is after
they're dead.
All right, so fascinating way of thinking about it.
Now the גמרא Gemara debates whether this is actually true. So let's
just read one more line here. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: וכבר קדם אחריך. V'kvar kodam acharecha. ומי אמר אביי הכי? U'mi
amar Abaye hachi? Did אביי Abaye really say that? והתניא V'hatanya מתנת
שכיב מרע אימת קני, matnas sh'chiv mera aimas kani, when does it
take effect? אביי אמר עם גמר מיתה, Abaye amar im gmar mita,
at the moment of death. ורבא אמר לאחר גמר מיתה, V'Rava amar
l'achar gmar mita, after the moment of death. Okay, so according to
this version, אביי Abaye says that it takes place here. So in
that case, דבורה Dvora and שרה Sarah would both be equally in
line. They would both get it at the moment of death and
maybe they'd have to split it or something. Okay, so now we
shift away from this whole issue of קנין פירות kinyan peiros to
discussing when does מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera take effect? At
the moment of death or after death? And it would seem like
a completely academic question, but here's a נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Somebody
is in line to get it at the moment of death. Does
מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Sh'chiv Meira come at the same time as
ירושה yerusha or does it come afterwards? Okay, and we have a
contradiction within אביי Abaye whether אביי says it's עת גמר מיתה as
gmar misa or אחר גמר מיתה. achar gmar misa. So we will
continue with this tomorrow and now I think we have to officially
say we're back to being on schedule. Sadly, we're no longer a
דף ahead. Okay, but anyway, so we are back to being on
schedule and we will pick up here tomorrow.